Emir Rodriguez Monegal Papers, 1941-1985 (bulk 1965-1968 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Series 1: Correspondence, dates not examined; 16 boxes
  - Zorrilla, Concepción, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 41)
  - Unidentified, dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 42-43)
- Series 2: Articles, Reviews, Notes, 1959-1960; 4 folders
  Consists of manuscripts and typescripts for articles, reviews, and notes such as "Cuba: la escritura de su historia," "Isidoro Ducase, lector del barroco español," and "Retratos y autorretratos: el hombre Freud y su biógrafo," as well as others. Also includes appointment books.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Articles, Reviews, Notes: A - G, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - "Albert Camus," ANs with holograph corrections, dates not examined; 9 pp. (Folder 1)
    - "Carta abierta al Presidente Kennedy," TMs, pp. numbered [1]-4, dates not examined; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - "Carta del Uruguay," TMs with holograph corrections, dates not examined; 3 pp. (Folder 1)
    - "Cuba: la escritura de su historia," TMs with holograph corerections, dates not examined; 11 pp. (Folder 1)
      [on Guillermo Cabrera Infante, "Vista del amanecer en el trópico"]
    - "El espectáculo más grotesco, ete." AMs with holograph corrections, dates not examined; 15 pp. (Folder 1)
    - "Gabriel García Márquez & Mario Vargas Llosa: "La novela en América Latina: Diálogo," TMs, dates not examined; 1 pp. (Folder 1)
    - Spanish version TMs with holograph corrections, dates not examined; 1 p. (Folder 1)
  - Articles, Reviews, Notes: I, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - Informe[s] sobre: ‘"De perfil," "Inventando el sueño," de José Agustín,' ‘"Extracción de la piedra de la locura," poemas de Alejandra Pizarnik,' ‘"Los días contados," novela de Fernando Alegría,' ‘"Siberia Blues," novela de Néstor Sánchez,' ‘"Jorge, un brasileiro," novela de Osvaldo França Jr.,' ‘"Los parientes," novela de Ricardo Prieto,' TMss, dates not examined; 13 pp. (Folder 2)
    - "Isidoro Ducase, lector del barroco español," TMs with holograph corrections, pp. numbered [1]-38, dates not examined; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Articles, Reviews, Notes: J - Z, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - "La nueva literatura argentina," TMs with holograph corrections, dates not examined; 1 p. (Folder 3)
    - "Personalidades: Alain Robbe-Grillet," TMs, pp. numbered 1-5, for El País (Madrid, September 19, 1962), dates not examined; portion of 1 folder (Folder 3)
    - "Retratos y autorretratos: el hombre Freud y su biógrafo," ANs, dates not examined; 8 pp. (Folder 3)
    - "Símbolos en la obra de Jorge Luis Borges, TMs with holograph corrections (Xerox), pp. numbered [1]-15, dates not examined; portion of 1 folder (Folder 3)
    - "Sobre una guía crítica de la literatura actual," TMs with holograph corrections, pp. numbered [1]-4, dates not examined; portion of 1 folder (Folder 3)
    - Reviews of "The Three Trials of Manirema," and "The Misplaced Machine and other stories," by Jose J. Veiga," two drafts, TMss with holograph corrections, dates not examined; 4 pp. (Folder 3)
    - "El universo cataléptico de Samuel Beckett," ANs, dates not examined; 5 pp. (Folder 3)
    - Untitled, dates not examined; portion of 1 folder (Folder 3)
      [answer to a letter concerning an article that Rodriguez Monegal wrote on the prologue of Carlos Real de Azúa to "Los motivos de Proteo."]
  - Appointment Books, 1959-1960; 1 folder (Folder 4)
- Series 3: Papers of Others, dates not examined; 2 boxes
  Consists of the papers of others, such as Jorge Aguilar Mora, Carlos Delgado, and Juan Aguilar Mora, as well as others.
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Aguilar Mora, Jorge, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Aridjis, Homero, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - "Aristarco", dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Avilés Fabila, René, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - BBC (London), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Benarós, León, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Bendezú, Francisco, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Bloch-Michel, Jean, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Bustamante, Cecilia, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Cardenal, Ernesto, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Costa, Flávio Moreira Da, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Delgado, Carlos, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Donoso, José, dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 13-14)
  - Futoransky, Luisa, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Garcia Nieto, José, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Garmendia, Salvador, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Ibañez, Roberto, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - Libertella, Héctor, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 19)
  - Lugo, Aniceto, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 20)
  - Marra, Nelson, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  - Monat, Olympia, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  - Nieto, Carlos, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 23)
  - Novás Calvo, Lino, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 24)
  - Payen-Appenzeller, P., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Pendle, George, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Pico Estrada, Luis, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Salinas, Pedro, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Sánchez, Nestor, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Sánchez Peláez, Juan, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Sarduy, Severo, dates not examined; 2 folders (Folder 7-8)
  - Steiner, Carlo, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Trobo, Claudio, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Urbistondo, Vicente, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Wajda, Andrzej, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Zand, Nicole, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Unidentified, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
- Series 4: Miscellaneous and Printed Material, 1954 October 24-1965; 2 boxes
  Consists of book orders, photographs, film reviews, press releases, and theater and movie programs, as well as other printed material.
  Arranged by genre of material.
  - Book Orders, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Revista Mundo Nuevo, dates not examined; 2 folders
    - Payments to Contributors, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - Travel & Entertainment Expenses, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - P. E. N. Club Meeting (Bled, Yugoslavia, 1965; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Film Reviews by Horacio Quiroga (photographs), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Marcha, no. 743 (Número Fantasma), 1954 October 24; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Newspaper & Magazine Clippings, dates not examined; 3 folders (Folder 3-5)
  - Press Releases, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Publishers' Book Lists, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Theater & Movie Programs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
- Series 5: Audio Recordings, 1956-1984; 3 boxes
  Consists of recordings originally on audiocassette and reel-to-reel featuring interviews Emir Rodriguez Monegal conducted with various Latin American writers as well as conference and seminar procedings.
  Arranged following the creator's order A1-A8 (interviews); B1-B3 (conferences); C1-C4 (lectures and interviews); D1-D2 (seminars and conferences); E1 (Latin American Novel program)
  - Interview: ERM / Maria Bonatti - About Borges (A1), undated; 1 folder (Item 1)
    32101047382393_1_a.mp3
    1 audiocassette; Side A written description on tape: Entrevista sobre a Biografía de Borges / Maria Bonatti. Side B written description on tape: [none].
    Side B is blank.
  - Interview: ERM / Jose Donoso (A2), 1970; 1 folder (Item 2)
    32101047382401_1_a.mp3
    32101047382401_2_a.mp3
    1 audiocassette; Side A written description on tape: Con't Donoso / ERM. Side B written description on tape: Entrevista José Donoso (Barcelona, Agosto 8, 1970).
    From digitization transfer notes: Side A: Program in silence from approximately 00:12 until 04:06, speed fluctuates throughout program on tape. Side B: Feedback heard throughout program on tape, gradual increase in speed throughout program on tape.
  - Interview: ERM / Juan Carlos Onetti (A3), Tape 1-2, undated; 1 folder (Item 3)
    32101047382419_1_a.mp3
    32101047382419_2_a.mp3
    32101047382427_1_a.mp3
    32101047382427_2_a.mp3
    2 audiocassettes; Tape 1, Side A written description on tape: Onetti / ERM Tape 1 A3 1a Side B written description on tape: b A3. Tape 2, Side B written description on tape: Onetti / ERM Tape 2 A3 3a. Side B written description on tape: 3b A3
  - Interview: ERM / Octavio Paz (A4), 1979; 1 folder (Item 4)
    32101047382435_1_a.mp3
    32101047382435_2_a.mp3
    1 audiocassette; Tape 1, Side A written description on tape: Octavio Paz/Oct. 25/1979 (NY) A4. Side B written description on tape: ERM / O. Paz
    From digitization transfer notes: The whole recording is faint, hard to hear anything; a hum can be heard throughout the tape.
  - Interview: ERM / Manuel Puig (A5), Tape 1-2, 1969; 1 folder (Item 5)
    32101047382443_1_a.mp3
    32101047382443_2_a.mp3
    32101047382450_1_a.mp3
    32101047382450_2_a.mp3
    2 audiocassettes; Tape 1, Side A written description on tape: Manuel Puig / Entrevista 17 / VIII / 69 (Bs Aires). Side B written description on tape: A5. Tape 2, Side B written description on tape: ERM /Puig A5 Tape 2. Side B written description on tape: A5.
    From digitization transfer notes: Sound is hard to hear; pitch of speakers is very high; sped up in certain parts of recording.
  - Interview: ERM / Severo Sarduy (A6), 1969; 1 folder (Item 6)
    32101047382468_1_a.mp3
    32101047382468_2_a.mp3
    1 audiocassette; Tape 1, Side A written description on tape: Severo Sarduy Cobra (II) A6. Side B written description on tape: Severo Sarduy: Cobra (II) / Escrito sobre un cuerpo
    From digitization transfer notes: Very faint sound/bit of a hum starting at 20:07 until 21:00. Date of interview: August 6, 1969.
  - Interview: ERM / Mario Vargas Llosa (A7), undated; 1 folder (Item 7)
    32101047382476_1_a.mp3
    32101047382476_2_a.mp3
    1 audiocassette; Side A written description on tape: Vargas Llosa. ERM más inteligible A7. Side B written description on tape: [similar infomation as other side].
  - Interview: Fitas / ERM, Tape 1-2 (A8), undated; 1 folder (Item 8)
    32101047382484_1_a.mp3
    32101047382484_2_a.mp3
    32101047382492_1_a.mp3
    2 audiocassettes; Tape 1, Side A written description on tape: Fitas / Monegal Tape 1 A8. Tape 1, Side B written description on tape: Monegal "Borges" A8. Interview conducted in Portuguese, about Borges. Tape 2 written description on tape: [similar or same infomation as other side].
  - ERM: Conference (B1), 1978; 1 folder (Item 9)
    32101047382500_1_a.mp3
    32101047382500_2_a.mp3
    1 audiocassette; Side A written description on tape: Conferencia do prof. Mongeal: A parodia e carnavalização na literatura moderna (B1). Side B written description on tape: [similar or same infomation as other side]. Written on case: Fae de letras Conferencia, junho 1978 UERT. Conference took place in Brazil, 1978.
  - Conference: ERM: Conference #1-6 (B2), 1982; 1 folder (Item 10)
    32101047382518_1_a.mp3
    32101047382518_2_a.mp3
    32101047382526_1_a.mp3
    32101047382526_2_a.mp3
    32101047382534_1_a.mp3
    32101047382534_2_a.mp3
    32101047382542_1_a.mp3
    32101047382559_1_a.mp3
    32101047382559_2_a.mp3
    32101047382567_1_a.mp3
    6 audiocassettes; Written description on case tapes: Prof. Emir Rodriguez Monegal Conferencia: "Tradução para Teatro". 25/08/82 Faculdade Ibero-Americana S. Paulo
    The following sides are blank: 32101047382542_2, 32101047382567_2
  - Readings: ERM / José Lezama Lima (B3), 1967; 1 folder (Item 1)
    32101047382575_1_a.mp3
    32101047382575_2_a.mp3
    1 audiocassette.
  - Lecture: Blanco, Tape 1-2 (C1), 1981; 1 folder (Item 2)
    32101047382583_1_a.mp3
    32101047382583_2_a.mp3
    32101047382591_1_a.mp3
    32101047382591_2_a.mp3
    2 audiocassettes; Lecture, Austin, 1981. Recording is in Spanish and Portuguese.
  - Interview: Susana Haydn / Jorge Luis Borges (C2), 1975; 1 folder (Item 3)
    32101047382609_1_a.mp3
    32101047382609_2_a.mp3
  - Readings: Pablo Neruda III (C3), undated; 1 folder (Item 4)
    32101047382617_1_a.mp3
    32101047382617_2_a.mp3
    1 audiocassette; poetry readings with Pablo Neruda. Side B is disrupted by musical recording.
  - Interview: Julia Kushsian / Severo Sarduy (C4), 1982; 1 folder (Item 5)
    32101047382625_1_a.mp3
    32101047382625_2_a.mp3
    1 audiocassette; interview with Severo Sarduy, by Julia Kushsian.
  - Conference? (About Aura by Carlos Fuentes)(D1), undated; 1 folder (Item 6)
    32101047382633_1_a.mp3
    32101047382633_2_a.mp3
    1 audiocassette; recording is in English.
  - Seminar (About E.A. Poe, possibly by J.L. Borges), Tape 1-2 (D2), undated; 1 folder (Item 7)
    32101047382641_1_a.mp3
    32101047382641_2_a.mp3
    32101047382658_1_a.mp3
    32101047382658_2_a.mp3
    2 audiocassettes; recording is in English.
  - "Ideas on Magic and Revolution: The Latin American Novel." Four part series from Canadian radio, written and presented by Toronto Writers #1-4 (E1-E2), 1984; 1 folder (Item 8)
    32101047382666_1_a.mp3
    32101047382666_2_a.mp3
    32101047382674_1_a.mp3
    32101047382674_2_a.mp3
    32101047382682_1_a.mp3
    32101047382682_2_a.mp3
    32101047382690_1_a.mp3
    32101047382690_2_a.mp3
    32101047382708_1_a.mp3
    32101047382708_2_a.mp3
    5 audiocassettes (two copies of last volume); Four part series from Canadian radio, written and presented by Toronto Writers, conducted between February 9 - March 1, 1984. Includes comments and passages from novels and poetry by Asturias, Carpentier, García Márquez, Fuentes, Cortázar, Vargas Llosa, Infante. Recording is in English.
  - "Memoria: Canciones en el Exilio". (Argentina), undated; 1 folder (Item 9)
    32101047382716_1_a.mp3
    32101047382716_2_a.mp3
    1 audiocassette; recording is in Spanish.
  - PEN Club - Versión Original / Versión Español 1-3, undated; portion of 1 box (Item 1)
    32101047383474_1_a.mp3
    32101047383474_2_a.mp3
    32101047383482_1_a.mp3
    32101047383490_1_a.mp3
    32101047383508_1_a.mp3
    4 audio reels; Side B of asset 32101047383482 is blank; Side B of asset 32101047383490 is blank; Side B of asset 32101047383508 is blank.
  - Spanish Lecture: Emir Rodriguez Monegal - Latin American Contemporary Novel, 1968; portion of 1 box (Item 2)
    32101047383516_1_a.mp3
    32101047383516_2_a.mp3
    1 audio reel; recorded on December 5, 1968. Recording is in English.
  - Leopoldo Torre Nilsson, Gustavo Sainz, Homero Aridjis, undated; portion of 1 box (Item 3)
    32101047383524_1_a.mp3
    32101047383524_2_a.mp3
    1 audio reel; recording is in Spanish.
  - Juan Goytisolo, Severo Sarduy, Oscar Lewis, Carlos Fuentes, ERM, Silvia Rudni, Maurice Coindreau, Graciela Martinez, Leonor Fini, E. Souchere / Conference: ERM, Beatriz Guido, Leopoldo Torre Nilsson, undated; portion of 1 box (Item 4)
    32101047383532_1_p1_a.mp3
    32101047383532_1_p2_a.mp3
    32101047383532_1_p3_a.mp3
    32101047383532_2_a.mp3
    1 audio reel; Side A was split into three different parts during digitization; some distortion is present; recording is in Spanish, English, and French.
  - Tercera Cinta del Archivo: ERM/Pettorutti, ERM/Torre Nilsson, ERM/Beatriz Guido, Cecilio Madanes, CFM/Pierre Kalfon, 1967; portion of 1 box (Item 5)
    32101047383540_1_p1_a.mp3
    32101047383540_1_p2_a.mp3
    32101047383540_2_a.mp3
    1 audio reel; recorded on July 13, 1967. Side A was split into two different parts during digitization; some distortion is present in part 2 (37:36 - about 41:00 and around 1:12:30- 1:12:58)
  - Manuel Rabat Taylo Martines de Alcalá Madrid, España, 1967; portion of 1 box (Item 6)
    32101047383557_1_a.mp3
    1 audio reel; interview took place - March 19, 1967 in Paris. Side B is blank.
  - [Blank], 1977; portion of 1 box (Item 7)
    32101047383565_1_p1_a.mp3
    32101047383565_1_p2_a.mp3
    1 audio reel; recorded on June 12, 1977 in Spanish. Side A was split into two different parts during digitization.
  - 1 empty envelope, undated; portion of 1 box (Item 8)
  - Emir Rodriguez Monegal record (33 1/3 rpm): "La Nueva Literatura Uruguaya" ( 1956 Audición Biblioteca Nacional), 1 box
- 32101037695150 (Box 1)
- 32101037695168 (Box 2)
- 32101037695176 (Box 3)
- 32101037695184 (Box 4)
- 32101037695192 (Box 5)
- 32101037695200 (Box 6)
- 32101037695218 (Box 7)
- 32101037695226 (Box 8)
- 32101037695234 (Box 9)
- 32101037695242 (Box 10)
- 32101037695259 (Box 11)
- 32101037695267 (Box 12)
- 32101037695275 (Box 13)
- 32101037695283 (Box 14)
- 32101037695291 (Box 15)
- 32101037695309 (Box 16)
- 32101037695317 (Box 17)
- 32101037695325 (Box 18)
- 32101037695333 (Box 19)
- 32101037695341 (Box 20)
- 32101037695358 (Box 21)
- 32101047385362 (Box 22)
- 32101047385354 (Box 23)
- 32101047385370 (Box L-000025)